I would say that building a relationship
is incredibly important because when you
move away from hey letting Apple handle
all the subscription stuff. The reality
is Apple does solve a lot of problems
that you don't have to think about and
users know how that works. When you are
on web that's your problem now and you
have the trust of the customer. So
everything from taking the payment to
cancelling your subscription to changing
plans to requesting a refunds to the
customer support to potentially handling
chargebacks. You have to get incredibly
good at that as a cable stakes because
if not you're either just making money
or people that have no clue how to
cancel subscription or even worse like
that's just going to destroy your app
reviews and you're going to get flagged
with all the credit card system. So the
billing sort of work stream of the
journey needs to be just super polished.
Hello, I'm your host David Bernard.
Today's conversation is shorter than
usual and will be featured in Revenue
Cat's state of subscription apps report.
Each episode in this series will explore
one crucial topic and share actionable
insights from top subscription app
operators. With me today, Leon Sassin,
co-founder and CTO at Rise Science. On
the podcast, I talk with Leon about why
web onboarding should sell the problem
instead of the solution, how discounted
paid trials are beating free trials, and
why creative that flopped for app ads
might just crush it for webfunnels. Hey
Leon, thanks for joining me again on the
podcast.
>> Hey David, good to be here. It's been a
minute since uh last time and the
revenue cat conference. Good times good
time since.
>> Yeah, always good to chat with you and
and the topic of web is something you
and I have talked a lot about over the
years. You were one of the early folks.
I mean I remember talking with you at
MAU gosh four years ago or something
about Stripe and chargebacks and like
the challenges you were having. So
you've been around the block and I know
in the last year you've found some
things that are finally really clicking
and so I was excited to have you on to
to talk about that and like what's
what's working and why it's working and
I think you know you're super
introspective and super into data and so
I feel like we're going to get a really
fresh perspective. So tell me what's
working and why is it working? Oh man,
it depends who you ask, but uh yeah,
we've been working on we've been trying
to up on work on web stuff for a long
long time. Probably in earnest around 20
end of 21 early 2022 when the whole IDFA
kind of at scan period of time that it
kind of wrecked everything for everyone.
So it was a time of people really and us
too freaking out about right all right
what's the future right like is mobile
marketing dead because for a few months
it was totally dead and the obvious
first order thing to do was like all
right let's do web funnels and that was
you know early 2002 so you sort of tried
that a few times and back then I would
say there were some large players in the
space doing it was more e-commerce but
you still had some maybe like n was the
biggest web funnel at the time as is I
believe so back then I'll start with
everything that wasn't working. So we
did that for a while and we were like
all right we need to figure out web and
that was pretty naive hey let's rebuild
our app on boarding in web right that's
kind of all right let's do that we did
that didn't quite work did that again
maybe 6 months later we just couldn't
get it to work like not even close and
we kind of gave up and we sort of
scratched it as like hey our app relies
too much on healthg data and all these
like cool features that are deep
integrations on your phone. So maybe
that's why it doesn't work on web
because we don't have your healthcare
data and we don't have all these sort of
deep integrations with your wearables
and your you know sleep schedule and all
of that. So we sort of parked that
project and also at that point all the
the marketing world started working a
little better on app. So the whole kind
of IDFA apocalypse it was definitely bad
but things recovered and and the big
publish you know like meta and Google
and just everyone kind of like figure
out how to work with the new system.
Even though it was painful, there was a
a path forward. So, we kind of kept
chugging along, working on core, you
know, making our app better and focusing
entirely on our app. And really, maybe
in 2024 or so, so now 2 years ago, we're
like, all right, let's give web another
another shot. And we never gave up
truly. It was more about, hey, now it's
not the time, but we know it's a big
opportunity. And maybe the naive take
and maybe that was our third attempt was
hey it still needs to look similar to
the app and it's helpful to kind of like
bypass some of the Apple fees or
whatnot. Very quickly kind of talking to
some people and learning it was like
right those two things are pretty wrong.
And first of all it changes the dynamic
so much that the apple building thing is
totally almost comparing like apples to
oranges. It's not even like remotely the
equivalent formula right like it's just
one small piece of the equation. And
second, once we talked to a few people
that have cracked it and kind of coaches
along the way and then sort of put us in
the right path, we we've also learned
that the way web funnels are successful
tend to be very different than the way
app on boarding flows tend to be
successful and they're almost like
fundamentally different parts of the
user journey. So you have to treat them
like that. So that kind of kicked off
really I mean hundreds and hundreds of
iterations to get the right mechanism of
what's going to work on web is different
than app and we should treat it as hey
it's a different surface a different
channel entirely from the marketing side
all the way to the user experience. So
we sort of started from scratch about
this is not at all related to the app,
right? This is a web funnel and let's
make that work unrelated to what works
on the app and and that kind of kicked
off a learning path that so far has been
super you know promising and super
productive. So happy to dive in in any
any areas there.
>> Yeah. Well, let's get specific when you
say you need to treat it as a whole
separate channel. What were the
learnings like? What why is the app
onboarding not working on the web? And
then how do you make that web specific
onboarding? Like what is it that people
are enticed by and resonating with on
the web that doesn't work in app and and
why does it work in app and not on the
web?
>> Yeah. The the thing that we learned on
our side, and this might kind of vary by
different developers and different
companies, but one of the things that
was pretty obvious from the get-go was
the audience, especially if you look at
it from the lens of, hey, you're
acquiring users through kind of paid
marketing or kind of like any atcale
marketing channels, the audience that
you often attract to a web funnel tends
to be very different than the audience
that you attract to an app funnel. And
there's obviously a little bit of
overlap because at the end of the day
the fundamental core user problem might
be similar. In our case it's like people
that might be exhausted in their lives
and are looking for a solution. Right?
That's a very kind of like overarching
theme but the audience is so different
that we found some marketing channels
down to the level of because the
campaigns tend to be web campaigns not
app campaigns. You tend to have a chance
to attract customers and users that are
not traditional app users. So they're
not the type of users that are going to
instinctively download an app as a
solution to random problems in their
lives, right? Whereas these are users
that would happily buy stuff online.
They're engaging e-commerce and they're
happy to kind of take a peek at
something and go deeper. And if the
solution happens to involve an app, you
might be able to convince them that this
is the right thing for them. But these
are not users that would traditionally
end up in sort of the the bottomfunnel,
hey, I'm going to download an app type
audience. So it's a lot more higher, you
know, top offunnel audience, which means
that a lot of what ends up working is
creating it as a lower intent to start,
but often high willingness to pay
because on some of these marketing
channels, you are attracting essentially
an e-commerce audience depending how you
do it. So it it ends up being because
the audience was different and and you
know, we can get into behavioral traits
of the audience, but even down to
demographics, the basic thing, right?
like you might be able to attract uh we
found that on web funnels we can attract
a lot older audiences like 40 50 60 year
old people at scale that maybe the app
you know the app the traditional app
marketing wasn't really able to reach
them who knows exactly why and then you
can imagine very quickly that the way
that you talk to a 50-year-old is very
different than the way we talk to a
30-year-old so especially in the lens of
of sleep and health right like the
problems might be very very different so
because the audience changes is then
you're starting essentially with a whole
new blank slate on on what works there.
So that's pretty high level but it was
pretty shocking that hey the audience is
different and and that brings a flip
side to the or a corlary to the
marketing that is because the audience
is different then the creative that
works can be very different on web than
app not all of it but some of it can be
very different which then means that in
a way webfunnel when you're running at
scale on say meta or google or whatever
other channel you might be running you
can end up where you have almost like
uncorrelated marketing performance
between different types of campaigns,
right? Like where you can have, you
know, everyone that markets might tell
you, oh, this month performance is down
and everyone's freaking out. And when
you run kind of web and app separate,
you realize like, oh, maybe like web is
down this month, but app is up or the
other way around. So you end up with a
actually a very different sort of cycle
that in a way just makes the ecosystem a
lot a lot healthier and more robust to
to you know flukes and performance. So
that's a bit of the high level that
we've learned on the website.
>> Are there specific channels or even
placements that you feel like do
especially well on web that you're
seeing a lot of success with? So like on
meta is it more the Facebook placements
than the Instagram placements or is it
you know Google versus Meta? Like are
you seeing any specific channels perform
better than others?
>> We find that generally speaking they all
work the same because the web audience
at least for us has leaned older. you
tend to see more shift towards the
Facebook blue app than Instagram, but
that's pretty high level and that es and
flows all the time depending on
creative. So on that side, there's not a
lot of differences. But on the creative
side, we often see creative that maybe
wasn't working on app that now starts
working on web and the other way around.
So you have more chances of winning when
you can try something twice and maybe
it's going to work on one side and not
the other because the audience is
different. So our job on the web is
we're getting people to realize the
problem they have which often is some
something that rhymes with hey you're
exhausted or you're you know you have
all these potential problems in your
life and you might not have realize that
sleep is the reason why you have those
problems. So we have this app that will
help you kind of take control and feel a
lot better and kind of unlock that part
of your life. So the the web funnel ends
up sort of we had to unlearn a lot of
the app on boarding that we spent a lot
of time crafting which was on the app it
was a lot about time to value. Hey get
to time to value get to the app moment.
You have as long as you want but you
really have to almost like impress the
user and give them value before you kind
of ask for a hard commitment of a trial
start or credit card or whatever. on
web, we realize that because people tend
to be a lot higher on the consideration
phase. Often you're you're just going
trying to go deeper on understanding the
problem and personalizing it, but not
going straight into solutions because
they might not be sold on the solution
yet. So just going out and trying to
tell them their plan and tell them all
the things that the features are going
to do, that might not work. Whereas
trying to understand and make realize
like, oh, this is the problem you have.
Let's now talk through solutions later
on the app. And it's sort of like a
separate phase and it's about helping
them realize that they might have a
problem and that we could have a
solution for them that they should try
out versus trying to go straight to the
aha moment of oh wow these people are
going to solve my problem you know on
the first 30 seconds because they're
just higher on the consideration phase
that they they just haven't downloaded
the app tend to be a different audience.
So we did have to unlearn a lot of that
product side. It actually makes a lot of
sense when you put it that way that when
you download an app, you're looking for
a solution. And so the the app
onboarding is to get you to a solution.
When you're see an ad on the web and
you're on a website, like I know when
I'm like surfing the web or like reading
about something, I'm I am more in the
discovery phase. Like what is it about
my sleep that's broken? What do I like
what do I need? And so it kind of makes
sense that the web onboarding needs that
more kind of exploratory
framing the the problem much deeper than
the app where people are just ready for
the solution. Would you say that kind of
perspective also informs creative or or
like is there any pattern between the
creative that's working on the web
versus what's working with app campaigns
that you're sending into the app?
>> There probably are. We just don't think
about it that way. We don't think about
like oh web creative versus app
creative. We think about our creative as
a, you know, much more deeper into what
customer personas we're trying to reach,
what hooks and value props we're trying
to kind of sell. And yes, because the
audience is different, but the creative
team doesn't really care. It just
happens that they get a different
persona or a different type of audience
that they're working on the creative. We
don't necessarily try crafting creative
for web. It's more like, hey, I don't
know, web has more females over 50 year
olds, so there's more creative for that
audience, let's say. Doesn't matter if
it's app or web. at least for our
current status.
>> So then are you trying most creatives on
both app and web simultaneously and just
letting the algorithms decide what wins
or or are you creating web specific
campaigns and app specific campaigns?
>> So that's a deep question. That's very
very deep. Creative testing at scale I
feel is the neverending sort of there's
always a hack always a system everyone
thinks they're better. Facebook tells
you or Meta or Google they'll tell you
what to do and then the experts tell you
to not do what the you know they tell
you the other people tell you to do. you
know, you got to try it all and I feel
every 6 months things change. But uh one
of the nice things about web is the
algorithm that learns for delivery tends
to be a lot so the algorithm the signal
and the measurement is a lot more
effective because the platforms in Omega
Google don't and Tik Tok and and
whatever else you may be they don't have
to deal with the sort of scan at privacy
related constraints that hey data is
delayed the attribution is broken you
get only see like 50% of the traffic
instead of 100%. So on web because it's
more traditional from the lens of the
advertising platform, web is essentially
an e-commerce which is a lot more easier
to pipe all the instrumentation into the
system. So the learning system is
faster. So it's a lot easier to run
those campaigns. One, and then two, the
algorithm tends to optimize a lot
faster. So you tend to find the people a
lot faster and you tend to know if
creative works a lot faster than on app
where you might not be able to like
really dive down and you might need to
wait a week or two to know if it's
working and depends on the budget. If
it's too low budget it might be longer.
So on web a lot of that iteration cycle
tends to be much much much faster which
is a huge unlock for for web. So it's
not necessarily about testing strategy.
You know we do test a lot of most
creative across both app and web
separately but at the beginning I
believe we may not even we might not
have been doing that. So it depends on
testing strategy and we're always
iterating on on that. So
>> I wanted to dive into a few tactical
things since we are running short on
time. Are are you spinning up a bunch of
different funnels? Like is it like are
you matching the funnel to the creative?
Like you know is there kind of a persona
bent where the do a creative with a a
specific persona in mind and then that
leads to a very specific funnel with
that persona in mind. Yeah, I think
that's the holy grail of web funnels
that you can actually go to the level of
the creative itself matches the funnel
in a way that app campaigns just cannot
do at all because the way you know you
have to download the app in the middle
of the flow. We do that to some extent.
It hasn't been a huge breakthrough yet
because it does require an order of
magnitude more complex kind of
operations between marketing and product
and coordination of everything. But we
are seeing very interesting success that
you can imagine where you can have very
different creatives and funnels for very
different personas and and it's all
customized. So we have some level of
customization, but we're going a lot
deeper on that because it does seem that
it's going to be another kind of huge
wave of unlocking when you can truly
personalize the experience for that
audience that they're coming from a very
specific type of user need. So, for
example, there's people that are tired
and want to sleep better because they
want to be more productive in the
morning. That's a very different persona
than your 50-year-old female that's, you
know, struggling with, you know,
sleepreated issues around menopause,
right? Which there's a whole kind of
body of science around and and what you
can do. So, very different personas. And
yes, in the funnel you can get into like
customizing different parts of the
experience, but if you can really tie
the funnel to the user audience that
you're reaching, you can just reach a
lot more people and let the algorithm
just find those people for you.
>> Last question, pricing and packaging.
Are you using different pricing and
packaging on the web versus the app? And
then even on specific funnels or
specific customizations, are you showing
them different offerings like only
monthly, monthly and annual, annual only
lifetime? How are you thinking about
pricing and packaging on the web versus
app and then even with individual
funnels?
>> Yeah. So the answer is for sure and
before I even say that I would say the
building relationship is incredibly
important because when you move away
from hey letting Apple handle all the
subscription stuff the reality is Apple
does solve a lot of problems that you
don't have to think about and you can
argue whether that's worth 30% or or
something else but Apple does solve the
problem for users and users know how
that works when you are on web that's
your problem now and and you have the
trust of the customer so everything from
taking the payment to canceling ing your
subscription to changing plans to
requesting refunds to the customer
support to potentially handling
chargebacks. You have to get incredibly
good at that as a table stakes because
if not, you're either just making money
on people that have no clue how to
cancel subscription or even worse,
right? Like that's just going to destroy
your app reviews and your credit card
sort of you're going to get flagged with
all the credit card system. So the
billing sort of work stream of the the
journey needs to be just super polished.
everything from starting to cancelling
to changing plans and that we just spend
a tremendous amount of time polishing
that as much as we can. So that cannot
be sort of an understatement of like oh
we'll do that later after with signal
because the other sort of caveat is if
you don't have all of that fleshed out
when you're testing the signal you get
you might see like oh your your trial
conversion is super high and it's like
oh well cuz you don't have a way to
cancel the subscription. So like of
course your child conversion is high but
like everyone is like super upset at you
because they don't have to cancel
subscription. So,
>> and you're getting high chargebacks and
high refunds, which means your your um
payment acceptance rate is lower. And
>> now back to your real question of
monetization packaging. I mean, like
everything we experiment a lot. We have
found two major learnings. One is yes,
it needs to be different. We tend to
skew to like shorter term plans. So,
monthly, quarterly, but we test
everything because we found the users
are in a very different consideration
phase. And then two, we tend to not
offer free trials on web, which is maybe
the biggest difference. And in some
cases, we do offer, but most of the time
we don't. And instead, we found that
offering heavily discounted trial
period, so hey, the first month might be
half the price or whatever measure it
might be ends up being a lot more
promising for a bunch of reasons. It
helps the algorithm optimize a lot
better. So, it's not finding people that
start trials and then automatically
cancel, you know, a minute later. So we
have found through testing that that
works better for us. I know some people
do find that free trials on web works
just as well. So I don't think this is a
like everything on pricing monetization
sort of depends heavily on your space
and your app and your brand. So
everything needs to be tested. But for
us, yes, pricing packaging is is very
different than the app directly.
>> All right, Leon, thank you so much for
sharing so many great insights. As we
wrap up, anything you wanted to share
with the audience? Are you hiring? Um,
anything our audience can do for you?
>> Yeah, of course, David. Like always, you
know, download the Rise app and uh most
people could use some help with with
their sleep. And then specific to our
company, we're always looking for
talented people across product,
engineering, design, and now marketing.
So, both UA and creative production. So,
definitely reach out and just generally
speaking, I love sharing notes with
other people in the app and consumer
space. So, the more you know, feel free
to reach out. You know, you don't have
to find me online. Leon rice.com.
Awesome. We we'll share links to your
LinkedIn and career page as well in the
show notes so people can go there as
well. But Leon, thank you so much. It
was great.
>> Thanks. Thanks for having me, David.
>> Thanks so much for listening. If you
have a minute, please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player. You can
also stop by chat.subclub.com
to join our private community. [music]